Guide to the Henry Onderdonk Papers ARC.045
Brooklyn Historical Society
- Series 2: Correspondence, 1835-1885; 1 Linear Feet
  A principal theme of Set 2-1 is the Revolutionary War, especially the Battle of Long Island and, to a lesser extent, the execution of Nathan Hale. The set also includes notes on genealogy, acknowledgements of receipts of Onderdonk's published works by individuals, libraries, etc.; invitations to readings, college commencements, celebrations, meetings, etc.; and requests of Onderdonk for historical and family history. Much of the correspondence takes the form of responses to specific Onderdonk requests for information, publications, etc. The bound correspondence includes some transcriptions of Long Island town records, including those of Jamaica, Flushing, and Hempstead. Hempstead history is a notable subject of the bound correspondence. Substantive correspondence in the set comes from authors and historians James Fenimore Cooper, George Bancroft, Charles Hoadly, Jared Sparks, Lorenzo Sabine, Thomas A. Strong, Benjamin F. Thompson, I.W. Stuart, and E.B. O'Callaghan. Other notable correspondents, though not necessarily conveying substantive matter, include John Breckinridge, James Buchanan, Washington Irving, William H. Seward, and Hamilton Fish, along with other U.S. senators, Congressmen, and state politicians. Correspondents that appear in other BHS collections include Henry Stiles, Henry Pierrepont, Jeremiah Johnson, and Henry Murphy.
  Set 2-2 also principally involves genealogy, requests for information, sharing information about the availability of particular books, and the like. The set includes a folder of correspondence with or about Quakers (Friends). Most notable in this regard is a letter from Rachel Hicks discussing Elias Hicks and Gideon Seaman, along with Quakers on Long Island in relation to American Indians, slavery, and the American Revolution. Also included in this set is correspondence from Onderdonk's former classmates at Harvard College and other Boston-area correspondents. Notable correspondents in this set include Lyman Draper commenting on the State Historical Society of Wisconsin, historian Jeptha Root Simms and Columbia College librarian William Alfred Jones commenting on various historical works or events, and Long Island genealogist Benjamin D. Hicks. Onderdonk's indexes and lists of names for this set are found in each folder.
  Set 2-3 includes requests of Onderdonk for information, publications, etc., and responses to Onderdonk's requests for same. The principal subject matter concerns genealogy, church history (especially Quakers and the Episcopal Church), and the American Revolution. Major correspondents include historians and genealogists Teunis Bergen, Jacob T. Bowne, Rev. Edward T. Corwin of Millstone, NJ, John J. Latting, and E.B. O'Callaghan. Other correspondents that can be found in BHS collections include Henry C. Murphy, Henry Stiles, and William S. Pelletreau. Requests for publications included correspondence from US senators and Congressmen, such as Roscoe Conkling, Hamilton Fish, and Dwight Townsend. A letter from William Pelletreau in the set's "miscellaneous research requests" referring to four beads of wampum may provide insight to the source of the wampum found in the Historical Manuscripts and Notes series. An 1875 letter from William Potts of Camden, NJ, surveys Quaker objections to slavery in New Jersey and Pennsylvania.
  Set 2-4 includes an 1856 letter from future president James Buchanan acknowledging his induction to the Long Island Bible Society, James Fenimore Cooper writing of British general Oliver de Lancey, E.F. Ellet corresponding with Onderdonk concerning her histories of the American Revolution (which emphasized women and domestic matters), and Gideon Frost, John Hicks, Benson Lossing, and James Riker on sources and writings concerning Long Island Quakers and Revolutionary War history.
  The series was compiled by the processing archivist from various sets, or individual items, of Onderdonk correspondence held by BHS. The series is arranged by these various sets as follows:
  Series 2-1: This consists of correspondence originally selected and bound together in two volumes by Onderdonk. The first volume has since been disbound, likely by a Brooklyn Historical Society archivist, with its contents re-arranged alphabetically by correspondent. The original index is in the second folder of the set. The second volume remains bound and in its original order. A detailed guide to the correspondence in set 2-1, prepared by a BHS archivist, is in the first folder.
  Series 2-2: This consists of correspondence in the numerical order assigned by Onderdonk.
  Series 2-3: This consists of correspondence categorized as research requests and arranged in alphabetical order, generally by correspondent. It is not known if this order was one established by Onderdonk or by a BHS archivist.
  Series 2-4: This consists of various other pieces of Onderdonk correspondence, arranged by the archivist alphabetically by correspondent.
  The series was compiled by the processing archivist from various sets of Onderdonk correspondence held by BHS. The series is arranged by these various sets as follows:
  Series 2-1 (1832-1869): Correspondence selected and bound together in two volumes by Onderdonk. The first volume has been disbound, with its contents re-arranged alphabetically by correspondent. The original index is in the second folder of the set. The second volume remains bound. A detailed guide to the correspondence in set 2-1 is in the first folder.
  Series 2-2: Correspondence in the numerical order assigned by Onderdonk.
  Series 2-3: Correspondence categorized as research requests by an archivist during an earlier phase of processing and arranged in alphabetical order, generally by correspondent.
  Series 2-4: Miscellaneous correspondence arranged alphabetically by correspondent.
  - Set 2.1: Supplementary Guide to Correspondence in Set 2.1 (Box 5, Folder 1)
  - Set 2.1: "A Selection of Historical Letters Addressed to Henry Onderdonk Jr." (41 folders), 1835-1869 (Box 5, Folder 2-41)
  - Set 2.1: "Historical Letters Addressed to Henry Onderdonk, Jr., 2nd Series.", 1838-1869 (Box 6, Folder 1)
  - Set 2.2: Letters Indexed by Correspondent (11 folders), circa 1840s-1880s (Box 6, Folder 2-12)
  - Set 2.3: Research Requests (21 folders), 1842-1885 (Box 7, Folder 1-21)
  - Set 2.4: Letters in Alphabetical Order by Correspondent (18 folders), 1844-1885 (Box 8, Folder 1-18)
    This set includes a list, circa 1878, of correspondents included in letters sent by Onderdonk to Brooklyn Historical Society.
- Series 3: Miscellaneous, 1729-1895; 0.25 Linear Feet
  The series is arranged by subject matter.
  The series includes a variety of original historical documents such as handbills, petitions, fliers, programs, and financial records related to various Long Island communities. Queens County is especially well-represented in the series, including various original invoices for expenses related to the transportation, maintenance, and execution of prisoners in Queens County; electoral campaign materials for temperance candidate Simon Craft (1846), advertisements for James M. Huntting's English and Classical Family School (1857), a share of stock in the Jamaica Circulating Library (1861), and other matter. Documents related to Union Hall Academy of Jamaica include student petitions, a list of students (1847), an advertisement with tuition rates, rules and other information, and student exhibition programs. For present-day Nassau County, documents include the program for the laying of the cornerstone at the Cathedral of the Incarnation in Garden City (1877), a Hempstead Seminary advertisement (1837), notices for public celebratory events at Little Neck (1857) and Manhasset (1872), and a 1793 document dividing land (likely at Cow Neck) between James Hewlett and George Rapelje. The series includes genealogical research notes and correspondence for the Dodge family of Long Island, a transcription of a French and Indian War era (1758) muster roll and related notes concerning a New York battalion from a regiment commanded by Col. Oliver de Lancey, and an account from a doctor's daybook showing services rendered (1729-1731).
  - Union Hall Academy, 1829-1871 (Box 8, Folder 19)
  - Dodge Family Genealogical Notes, 1878-1879 (Box 8, Folder 20)
  - French and Indian War-related, 1758 (Box 8, Folder 21)
  - Queens County Prisoner-related Expenses, 1783-1785 (Box 8, Folder 22)
  - Queens County Misc, 1791-1861 (Box 8, Folder 23)
  - Long Island Churches, 1833-1881 (Box 8, Folder 24)
  - Long Island Misc, 1837-1872 (Box 8, Folder 25)
  - Miscellaneous, 1729-1895 (Box 8, Folder 26)
- Series 4: Scrapbooks, circa 1788-circa 1882; 7 Linear Feet
  A seven volume set of scrapbooks Onderdonk finished compiling in 1869 concerning Queens County is first in the series, followed by an 1864 volume with material covering all three Long Island counties of the time (Kings, Queens, Suffolk).
  The date range used in the container list is the approximate date of the original documents in the scrapbooks. Some of the scrapbook documents, particularly in Queens County Volume 1, are mid-nineteenth century transcriptions, newspaper reprints of old items of interest such as town record entries, historical narratives published in newspapers, or other forms of secondary material concerning the seventeenth century and later; accordingly, a second date range, found within the item description, is used for the approximate date range of the historical period referred to by the content of the scrapbook documents.
  The content of the seven volume Queens County set advances in chronological order, covering historical matters from circa 1663 to 1868. Much of the material concerning the period until the 1820s are not contemporary documents; the earliest contemporary documents date from circa 1798. Several of the volumes include post-1868 handbills and other ephemera (i.e., material dating from after Onderdonk's completion of the scrapbooks) tipped-in to the scrapbooks at various places in no discernible order. The content of the earliest volumes in the set seem to adhere to a less rigorous organization than the later volumes which run in a reliable chronological order.
  The content of the one volume scrapbook includes well-defined sections on Kings, Queens, and Suffolk counties. The volume includes a subject index prepared by Onderdonk. There is also a partial list of contents at the front of the scrapbook prepared by a Brooklyn Historical Society librarian in 1940.
  The series includes eight scrapbooks compiled by Onderdonk in the 1860s. Seven of these scrapbooks, completed in 1869, comprise a set covering Queens County, which at the time also included the towns that would later become Nassau County. In these volumes, Jamaica, Flushing, and Hempstead are perhaps most prominent, but other locales, including Newtown, Oyster Bay, Cow Neck, Roslyn, and Glen Cove, are represented significantly. Occasional Kings County material appears, though not extensively; generally this material especially concerns Brooklyn and are often clippings from a series of historical pieces published by the Eagle. The bulk of the material consists of newspaper clippings; it is seldom clear which newspapers were the source of particular clippings, but at least three newspapers appear to have been significant sources: Democrat (Jamaica); Long Island Star; and Long Island Farmer and Queens County Advertiser. Some handbills, advertisements, circulars, and other such ephemera can also be found in the scrapbooks; in most instances, these items date from after the scrapbooks compilation date and are tipped-in at seemingly random places, such as a circa 1880 Manhattan Beach Railway timetable and map found in Volume 2.
  The clippings focus on Queens County matters of potential local historical interest, so broader New York or national events are not represented aside from their local connection, nor are literary or other fictional writings included. The subject matter of the clippings is wide-ranging, but there is also a high level of consistency across the seven volumes for several subjects. These subjects include political matters, such as accounts of political gatherings, detailed results by town of presidential, state, and local elections, and party positions; agriculture, such as agricultural society fairs (especially the Queens County Agricultural Society) and lists of premiums awarded by the societies; temperance and temperance societies; government matters, such as accounts of town meetings, meetings of town trustees or supervisors, and court proceedings; announcements, public notices and advertisements, such as those for public auctions, lectures to be given, openings and other events at schools, churches, and other institutions, camp meetings, stagecoach departure schedules, and recreational outings and events; financial information, such as taxpayer lists and assessments, town finances, and corporate operations; crimes (e.g., murder, rape, assault, theft) and accidental deaths (e.g., drownings, fires, falls); lists of interments; July 4 celebrations, including accounts of the toasts given; and railroad development and reports of operations. References to African-Americans, though not frequent, appear throughout the volumes in the context of the above subjects, such as runaway notices (Vol. 1), announcements of camp meetings (e.g., Vol. 4) or annual beach parties (Vol. 6 and 7), and in accounts of crimes, accidents or deaths.
  The first volume includes Revolutionary War events, including information on the prison ships and the refugees from Long Island. Volumes 6 and 7 include much on the Civil War as it relates to Queens County, such as town war meetings, lists of draftees, deaths, and regiment recruitment, musters, and other activities. Items with an obvious personal connection to Onderdonk are common, including material on Union Hall Academy and articles referring to individuals with the Onderdonk name. By 1866, the scrapbooks include box scores and summaries of local baseball games. The eighth scrapbook in the series was compiled at an earlier date, in 1864, than the seven volume set. The single volume includes Kings and Suffolk counties in its scope, as well as Queens County. The subject matter of this one volume is generally consistent with that described above. Because of the overlap in chronology, the Queens County section of this scrapbook can be viewed as a supplement to the seven volume set. The Kings County section of this scrapbook consists principally of a series of historical narratives published by the Brooklyn Eagle circa 1862.
  - Queens County, Vol 1 (1663-1829), circa 1798-circa 1880 (Box 9, Item 1)
  - Queens County, Vol 2 (1830-1836), circa 1830-circa 1881 (Box 10, Item 1)
  - Queens County, Vol 3 (1837-1843), circa 1837-circa 1880 (Box 10, Item 2)
  - Queens County, Vol 4 (1844-1849), circa 1844-circa 1877 (Box 10, Item 3)
  - Queens County, Vol 5 (1849-1856), circa 1849-circa 1856 (Box 11, Item 1)
  - Queens County, Vol 6 (1855-1864), circa 1855-circa 1864 (Box 12, Item 1)
  - Queens County, Vol 7 (1864-1868), circa 1864-circa 1868 (Box 11, Item 2)
  - Kings, Queens and Suffolk Counties (circa 1640-circa 1882), circa 1788-circa 1882 (Box 9, Item 2)